A Guide to the Perkins Family Papers, 1782-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Perkins Family Papers 1782-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-53
7 boxes and 57 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph W. Hazelgrove, 1933 January 9.
Scope and Content
A collection of personal, official, legal and business papers of the Perkins family of Cumberland, Buckingham and Powhatan counties, and later of Richmond and Charlottesville, all in Virginia. The relatively small amount of personal correspondence consists of letters of the 18th century to William Perkins of Buckingham county, a few of the early 19th century to George Perkins (d. 1834), and to Mrs. Eliza Perkins, widow of George Perkins. A considerable part of the collection consists of George Perkins' records as deputy sheriff; execution books, tax books, tax registers, lists of fees and fines, various ledgers, and numerous receipts to Perkins and copies of orders to him from various county courts all of the period 1800-1820. A number of account books and letter books, 1816-1825, were kept by a merchant George Perkins of Richmond, perhaps the aforementioned sheriff. Smaller groups of items include accounts, correspondence and financial documents of Dr. Robert Henderson, father-in-law to one of the Perkins men, ca. 1810-1860, and correspondence and papers of William A. Perkins, notably advertisements of sales of property to be held in Cumberland County, suggesting that he was at the time, 1860-1872, a sheriff or deputy sheriff. The Perkins papers also include notebooks of George Perkins (1846-1918) and William Merry Perkins (b. 1844) kept at the University of Virginia from 1865-1869, and large group of letter books of George Perkins; personal correspondence 1883-1918; legal correspondence as attorney for the City of Charlottesville, 1869-1914; legal correspondence representing his law practice as a member of the firm of Perkins and Perkins, 1903-1915. Additional items include account books of John T. Seabrook and Co. of Smithville in Powhatan County, 1842-1874, as well as the accounts of a blacksmith, 1849-1866, and a number of unidentified account books for the period 1835-1891. Other papers concern the Guthery, Henderson, Saunders, and Smith families.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1782-1858, 267 pieces: (Box 1)
  First few (18th century) to William Perkins of Buckingham, on land; those 1813-16 mostly to Geo. Perkins, deputy sheriff of Cumberland; others largely family, mostly to Mrs. Eliza Perkins, widow of George Perkins (d. Sept 30, 1834).
- Correspondence ca. 1811-1893, 333 pieces: (Box 2)
  Largely correspondence of William A. Perkins et al 1860-1862, and advertisements of personal property to be sold in Cumberland Co.
- Accounts ca. 1783-1809, 806 pieces: (Box 3)
  nearly all are receipts to George Perkins as deputy sheriff, not a few accounts for agriculture and other commodities to Henry Guthery, William Perkins and George Perkins.
- Accounts ca. 1810-1892, 738 pieces: (Box 4)
  about 1/2 to c. 1818 accounts and receipts to George Perkins as deputy Sheriff, and 1/2 to ca. 1861 to Robert Jennsen; few relate to William H. and various other Perkins names.
- Legal papers 1789-1893, 745 pieces: (Box 5)
  mostly rec., orders to George Perkins, ca. 100 of Robert Henderson (mostly notes), from William Perkins et al. 3 Cumberland Co. registers poll and land tax 1808-1809.
- Ledgers, etc. 1807-1867 (Box 6)
  Letter Book etc., Martha Eliza Henderson; exercise books at UVA 1865-67 George Perkins, account books of George Perkins as deputy Sheriff; execution books 1807-1809, 1811-1812, 1812-1813; tax books, 1809, 1817- 1819; ledgers 1816-1820?, 1818-1819?, 9 vols. William Merry Perkins (b.1844) Buckingham C.H. UVA 1860-1861, 1865-1866.
- 11 pieces unbound college notebooks of George Perkins at UVA 1801-1867, 8 vols: (Box 7)
  1) Latin composition notebook 1865, with notes of personal expenditures 1865-1867, etc; 2-3) French notebooks 1863-1866, 1866-1867 (with draft or drafts of speech or speeches, etc.); 4) natural philosophy 1866- 1867 (with 2 short plays in MS., a different hand). College notebook of William M. Perkins, senior law at UVA, N.D., vol 1865-1866; Execution books of George Perkins 1805-1807, 1807-1809, Tax book 1812, George Perkins list of fees 1801, militia fines 1801. List of fees 1802, of taxable property 1806, of fees due 1806 (2), of land taxes 1806 (4), ditto 1807 (2). Letter and account book of George Perkins 1817.
- Tax book 1817 (Volume [1])
  with accounts (day book) of a blacksmith 1862-1866.
- Account book (day book?), Richmond 1816-1817 (Volume [2])
- Law notebook, George Perkins, UVA, Session 1867-1868 (Volume [3])
- George Perkins Day book, Richmond 1817-1819 (Volume [4])
  continues (2) above.
- Ledger 1817-1819 (Volume [5])
- Account book (day book?) Richmond, probably by George Perkins 1817-1819 (Volume [6])
- Law notebook, George Perkins, UVA Session 1867-1868 (Volume [7])
  with accounts of George Perkins as administrator [loose papers of George Perkins, 1876 and 1890, laid in (8)].
- Account book (day book?), Richmond 1819-1820 (Volume [8])
  with a diary 1836 Oct 17-Dec 15; and Day Book (?) 1835-1845; and a diary 1844 Nov 19-June 6 same hand as; misc. accounts 1835-1845.
- Account Book: misc. accounts, often of estates 1862-1883 (Volume [9])
- Law Notebook, George Perkins, UVA Session 1868-1869 (Volume [10])
- Account Book: misc. goods 1881-1891 (Volume [11])
- Account Book: tobacco purchases & sales 1877 (Volume [12])
- Letter Book, George Perkins and Perkins & Harris, Richmond (tobacco merchants?) 1820-1824 (Volume [13])
- Account Book 1821-1825 (Volume [14])
  1821-1822, 1824-1825, Richmond; misc; 1853-1857, blacksmith account?
- Blacksmith's account book 1849-1874 (Volume [15])
- Account Book, Leedlam Henieken & Co (?) 1864-1874 (Volume [16])
  misc. accounts, tobacco shipments?
- Account Book, Dr. Robert Henderson 1839-1858 (Volume [17])
- Account Book: Richmond receipts to Geo. Perkins for misc. goods 1817-1818 (Volume [18])
  with Letter Book of Geo. Perkins, Richmond, 1817-1818.
- Letter Book, Perkins and Perkins, Out-letters. Aug-Dec 1904 (Volume [19])
- Letter Book, Perkins and Perkins Dec. 1904-March 1905 (Volume [20])
- Account Book, Richmond 1820-1821 (Volume [21])
  Receipts to Geo. Perkins for receiving payments of money.
- Account Book, Richmond (Day book?) 1819-1821 (Volume [22])
- Account Book 1819-1821 (Volume [23])
- Day Book, John T. Seabrook & Co., Smithville, Powhatan Co. 1842-1843 (Volume [24])
  with Day Book (?) 1858-1860 of a blacksmith.
- Day Book, Geo. Perkins, Richmond 1821-1822 (Volume [25])
  Sales of tobacco, wheat, flour, lumber.
- Letter Book, Geo. Perkins, Richmond, Out-letters 1818-1820 (Volume [26])
- Account Book 1816-1817 (Volume [27])
- Account Book, Geo. Perkins, Richmond 1818-1821 (Volume [28])
- Letter Book, Perkins and Perkins, Out-letters Dec 1905-March 1906 (Volume [29])
- Letter Book Aug-Dec 1905 (Volume [30])
- Letter Book March-Aug 1905 (Volume [31])
- Letter Book, George Perkins activity for city of Charlottesville Jan 1906-Dec 1914 (Volume [32])
  1896-1915 out-letter.
- Letter Book, George Perkins, private, Out-letters Jan 1883-July 1886 (Volume [33])
- Letter Book, Perkins & Perkins, Out-letter Nov 1903-Apr 1904 (Volume [34])
- Letter Book Sept-Dec 1912 (Volume [35])
- Letter Book Feb-Sept 1912 (Volume [36])
- Letter Book Sept 1911-Feb 1912 (Volume [37])
- Letter Book Apr-Sept 1911 (Volume [38])
- Letter Book Nov 1910-Apr 1911 (Volume [39])
- Letter Book July-Nov 1910 (Volume [40])
- Letter Book March-July 1910 (Volume [41])
- Letter Book Nov 1909-March 1910 (Volume [42])
- Letter Book June-Nov 1909 (Volume [43])
- Letter Book Apr-Sept 1908 (Volume [44])
- Letter Book Nov 1907-Apr 1908 (Volume [45])
- Letter Book Apr 1907-Nov 1907 (Volume [46])
- Letter Book Nov 1906-Apr 1907 (Volume [47])
- Letter Book July-Nov 1906 (Volume [48])
- Letter Book March-July 1906 (Volume [49])
- Letter Book Feb-June 1909 (Volume [50])
- Letter Book, George Perkins, Activity for city of Charlottesville Nov 1896-Dec 1905 (Volume [51])
- Letter Book, George Perkins; personal? Aug 1886-Nov 1908 (Volume [52])
- Letter Book, George Perkins? Aug 1908-Jan 1909 (Volume [53])
  City activity? Pers? P & P? Illegible; Out-letter.
- Letter Book, Perkins, Perkins & Walker Feb 1913-Jan 1915 (Volume [54])
- Letter Book, George Perkins, private, Out-letters Sept 1915-Jan 1915 (Volume [55])
- Letter Book, George Perkins, private Nov 1908-Aug 1915 (Volume [56])
- Miscellaneous Accounts 1859-1860 (Volume [57])
  Receipts to W. A. Perkins 1866-1867; List of items sold (at auction, eg?); Letter Book W. A. Perkins 1871-1872; miscellaneous accounts.